<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G18">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geography and Environmental Management, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2018</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Estimation of Phytoplankton Chlorophyll-a Concentration in the Western Basin of Lake Erie Using Sentinel-2 and Sentinel-3 Data</title>
			<author>
				<first>Somayeh</first>
				<last>Mollaee</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Worldwide phenomena called algae bloom has been recently a serious matter for inland water bodies. Temporal and spatial variability of the bloom makes it di cult to use in-situ monitoring of the lakes. This study aimed to evaluate the potential of Sentinel-3 Ocean and Land Colour Instrument (OLCI) and Sentinel-2 Multispectral Instrument (MSI) data for monitoring algal blooms in Lake Erie. Chlorophyll-a (Chl-a) related products were tested using NOAA-Great Lakes Chl-a monitoring data over summer 2016 and 2017. Thematic water processor,  fluorescence line height/maximum chlorophyll index (MCI) and S2 MCI, plug-in SNAP were assessed for their ability to estimate Chl-a concentration. We processed both Top of the Atmosphere (TOA) reflectance and radiance data. Results show that while FLH algorithms are limited to lakes with Chl-a &lt; 8 mg m-3, MCI has the potential to be used effectively to monitor Chl-a concentration over eutrophic lakes. Sentinel-3 MCI is suggested for Chl-a &gt; 20 mg m-3 and Sentinel-2 MCI for Chla &gt; 8 mg m-3. The different Chl-a range limitation for the MCI products can be due to the different location of the maximum peak bands, 705 and 709 for MSI and OLCI sensors respectively. TOA radiances showed a signi cantly better correlation with in situ data compared to TOA reflectances which may be related to the poor pixel identi cation during the process of pixel flagging affected by the complexity of Case-2 water. Our fi nding suggests that Sentinel-2 MCI achieves better performance for Chl-a retrieval (R2 = 0.90). However, the FLH algorithms outperformed showing negative reflectance due to the shift of reflectance peak to longer wavelengths along with increasing Chl-a values. Although the algorithms show moderate performance for estimating Chl-a concentration; this study demonstrated that the new satellite sensors, OLCI and MSI, can play a signi ficant role in the monitoring of algae blooms for Lake Erie.</abstract>
			<url hash="7b729893">G18-1001</url>
			<doi>10012/13456</doi>
			<bibkey>Mollaee-2018-Estimation</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Preferential flowpaths and fertilizer placement influence subsurface P transport across soil textures and seasonal conditions</title>
			<author>
				<first>Kirsten</first>
				<last>Grant</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Agricultural tile drains are a source of phosphorus (P) contributing to eutrophication. Preferential flowpaths can rapidly transport P to tile drains, but their activation in different soil textures and under variable seasonal conditions (antecedent moisture conditions and presence of soil frost) is not well understood. Subsurface placement of fertilizer has been proposed as a management practice to reduce P loss, compared to surface applications. However, how subsurface placement reduces P loss is not well understood. The goal of this thesis is to relate subsurface flowpaths and fertilizer placement to identify source and transport mechanisms controlling P movement to tile drains, across soil textures and seasonal conditions. A lab experiment was done on intact soil monoliths (clay, silt loam) to investigate interactions between fertilizer placement, subsurface flowpaths, and soil frost. Conservative water tracers (Brˉ, Clˉ and D₂O) applied through successive events identified matrix flow as the dominant flowpath in unfrozen silt loam, while preferential flow dominated in unfrozen clay and in both soil types under partially frozen conditions. Subsurface placement of fertilizer reduced dissolved reactive P losses by 60% in silt loam and 64% in clay over the simulated non-growing season compared to surface broadcast applications. A field study used blue dye as a tracer to investigate subsurface flowpaths in clay and silt loam plots under wet and dry conditions. Dye stain patterns were analyzed to determine the relative importance of matrix and macropore flow. Soil samples were collected to determine soil P distribution post-fertilization. Preferential flow occurred under all soil texture and moisture conditions. Dry clay soil showed the deepest staining (92 ± 7.6 cm), followed by wet clay (77 ± 4.7 cm). In silt loam soil, depth of staining did not differ between wet (56 ± 7.2 cm) and dry (50 ± 6.6 cm) conditions. Soil water-extractable P distribution varied with fertilizer application in the top 10 cm of the soil profile, but did not differ at depth. Together, the results of this research suggest subsurface placement is a suitable practice for minimizing subsurface nutrient loss, by reducing contact between the nutrient supply and preferential flowpaths, particularly in clay soils prone to preferential flow. This work provides an improved understanding of subsurface flowpaths carrying P to tile drains, and more broadly, solute transport through preferential flowpaths.</abstract>
			<url hash="e27bc929">G18-1002</url>
			<doi>10012/14248</doi>
			<bibkey>Grant-2018-Preferential</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="3">
			<title>Simulating Farmer Adoption of Agricultural Best Management Practices in the Upper Medway Creek Subwatershed</title>
			<author>
				<first>Liuyi</first>
				<last>Guo</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>In the coupled human-environment system, humans play a central role in creating various environmental problems, and in turn, are impacted by these environmental consequences. In Canada, water quality degradation caused by agricultural activities has become a severe problem for a long time. It has been noted that the application of pesticides, manure and fertilizers have led to an increasing amount of chemicals and other pollutants in surface runoff which eventually converge into surface water bodies and result in water eutrophication. To maintain water quality and develop a sustainable agricultural system, Best Management Practices (BMPs) have been suggested. However, the high complexity of the agriculture system makes it difficult for policymakers and researchers to monitor and evaluate the performance of BMPs across large spatial scales and develop appropriate improvement strategies accordingly. Under these circumstances, agent-based models (ABM) stand out for their ability to deal with the complexities in the agri-environment system. To better understand the dynamics of farmer’s decision-making on BMP application under different socio-economic and environmental situations, an ABM has been developed to simulate the decision-making processes in the Upper Medway Creek subwatershed in this study. The ABM uses an optimizing decision-making structure that relies on choice by highest utility. In addition, the ABM integrates a weighted sum function to evaluate the influences of economic, environmental and social factors on farmers’ decision-making. Results from the model pre-test were compared to those obtained from a random generator to examine how does the developed ABM perform against the random generator. Then, a sensitivity analysis has been performed using the one-factor-at-a-time method to examine the impacts of different potential interventions, including government subsidies and educational activities, on farmers’ decision-making for certain BMP adoptions.  The results demonstrated that the developed ABM is robust in simulating farmers’ decision-making on BMP application within the Upper Medway Creek subwatershed. According to the sensitivity analysis, providing subsidies and improving knowledge level of BMPs have positive effects on the implementations of certain BMPs in general. While comparing to improving knowledge levels of BMPs, providing subsidies makes greater contribution to motivating farmers to adopt BMPs. For each BMP, a subsidy rate, which indicates the proportion of implementation costs needs to be subsidized to effectively encourage the BMP adoption, has been suggested. The results of this study provide a better understanding of how different socio-economic conditions affect farmers’ decision-making on BMP adoptions and offer insights for policymakers to develop effective strategies incentivising farmers’ adoptions of BMPs and further preserving water quality in the Upper Medway Creek subwatershed.</abstract>
			<url hash="957cf9bf">G18-1003</url>
			<doi>10012/14003</doi>
			<bibkey>Guo-2018-Simulating</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Biology, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2018</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Developing pre-industrial baselines from floodplain lake sediment cores to quantify the extent of metals pollution within the Alberta Oil Sands Region</title>
			<author>
				<first>Wynona</first>
				<last>Klemt</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Oil sands mining operations began in 1967, but the onset of a monitoring program to assess water and sediment quality in the Athabasca River watershed began 30 years later. Consequently, no knowledge of pre-industrial, baseline conditions exists upon which current river sediment quality can be compared. This has undermined an ability to determine the relative importance of contaminants supplied by natural processes versus pollution to the Athabasca River by rapid growth of oil sands development. In this study, a paleolimnological approach was used to analyze sediment cores from five flood-influenced lakes located upstream and downstream of oil sands operations within the Alberta Oil Sands Region (AOSR). Loss-on-ignition and organic carbon and nitrogen elemental analyses were used to differentiate periods of strong and weak Athabasca River flood influence. In addition, the temporal changes in concentrations of bitumen-associated metals vanadium (V) and nickel (Ni) were explored at each lake. A pre-industrial baseline was developed using pre-1967 sediment concentrations of V and Ni, normalized to aluminum concentration, from lakes in the AOSR to estimate the natural range of variability of these metals. When normalized metals concentrations in recently deposited flood-influenced sediment were compared to the pre-industrial baseline, no evidence of enrichment in the river-derived stratigraphic intervals was detected. However, significant enrichment of bitumen-related metals V and Ni (up to 2- and 1.6-fold above the baseline, respectively) was observed in weakly flood-influenced sediment in the two floodplain lakes located closest to the most active mining operations (&lt; 10 km), indicating local atmospheric pollution. Athabasca River sediment data collected by regional monitoring programs RAMP (1997-2002) and JOSM (2012-2014) were examined in the context of the newly developed baselines and showed enrichment of V (1.2-1.7x baseline) and Ni (1.2-2.0x baseline) at some of the river monitoring sites, usually proximal to tributary outflows. This research indicates that sediment profiles from floodplain lakes along the lower Athabasca provide valuable information as pre-industrial depositional areas of natural sediment metals. Paleohydrological analyses, however, indicate that flood-influence at many of these lakes is declining, coincident with oil sands growth, and so many of the lakes no longer frequently capture flood sediments. Nonetheless, metal-specific baselines using the pre-1967 data can be used to detect enrichment in modern sediments of the floodplain lakes and in river sediment monitoring data, the latter previously criticized for inadequate baseline knowledge, and which also now serves as a foundation for ongoing river sediment monitoring.</abstract>
			<url hash="69c7377d">G18-2001</url>
			<doi>10012/14181</doi>
			<bibkey>Klemt-2018-Developing</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>School of Public Health and Health Systems, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2018</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Country Food Consumption Notices: Assessing Awareness and Preferences of Health and Risk Communication Messages in the Sahtú Region of the Northwest Territories</title>
			<author>
				<first>Danielle</first>
				<last>Brandow</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Background: Country food consumption by Indigenous peoples is associated with improved nutrition, food security, and lower rates of chronic diseases (Kuhnlein, Burlingame, &amp; Erasmus, 2013); however, these foods can also pose potential risks of exposure to contaminants such as mercury and cadmium (Berti, 1997). Elevated fish mercury concentrations in some lakes in the Sahtú region of the Northwest Territories (NWT) resulted in a series of consumption notices that suggested people limit their consumption of walleye, northern pike, and lake trout from specific lakes in the region (NWT, 2016). Therefore, as part of a health communication component was added. This component was designed to assess participants risk perceptions and awareness of current consumption notices and health messages, to provide baseline data to evaluate the impact of consumption notices, to determine how health messages are currently developed, and to make recommendations to create more targeted communication strategies.  Objectives: The research objectives of this thesis are to: 1) Assess participants’ risk perceptions and awareness of current consumption notices and health messages; 2) Provide baseline data to evaluate the impact of consumption notices and health messages over time; 3) Understand how consumption notices and health messages are currently developed and communicated to communities by the Government of the Northwest Territories; and 4) Make recommendations that aim to improve and create more effective communication strategies with focus in the Sahtú Region of the Northwest Territories based on knowledge synthesized from terminology workshop(s), surveys, and interviews. Methods:  This project involves a Health Messages Survey, two terminology workshops, community interviews, and stakeholder interviews. Participants were invited to take part in a Health Messages Survey where they were asked questions about their perceptions of contaminants, whether they had heard or seen consumption notices, in addition to their preferences for future health messages based on trust and accessibility. Two terminology workshops were implemented in Délı̨nę, where key terms from the human biomonitoring project were identified, in order to translate or interpret into Slavey language. Twelve interviews were conducted with community members in Délı̨nę to document perceptions and stories regarding contaminants. Interviews also took place in Yellowknife with stakeholders from the Government of the Northwest Territories, the Federal Government, the Dene Nation, and the Giant Mine Oversight Board.  Results: Based on the data collected by surveys (n=43), interviews (n=19) and two terminology workshops (n=27) during a two-year period from 2017-2018, we found that country foods are extremely valued in communities for many reasons. Each participant reported eating country foods and many preferred solely relying on country foods rather than: i) store-bought foods; or ii) a mix of store-bought foods and country foods. During community interviews, each participant expressed their gratitude for the country foods that they eat and wished that they could eat it more often. In the terminology workshops, the cultural importance of trapping, fishing, and hunting was discussed. Many participants had heard or seen messages that promoted the nutritional value of country foods and had also learned from their Elders and family members that these foods have been a source of sustenance for thousands of years. The majority of participants had heard or seen messages about fish with high levels of mercury in their country foods from radio, researcher or scientists, and friends and family. These participants also expressed their fear that contaminants may have impacted the country food that they most preferred to eat. The fear that participants expressed invoked change by the Government of the Northwest Territories (GNWT. The GNWT, the primary disseminator of health messages, has since changed their communication strategy from only consumption notices, to fact sheets and general fish consumption guidelines.  Conclusion: This project demonstrated the importance of country food in the Sahtú region. In the Sahtú country foods connects people to the traditional and cultural practices that were passed on by parents and Elders which provides a sense of community and of belonging. This project provides baseline data based on surveys, interviews and terminology workshops for a clearer picture of how these participants perceive contaminants, where they currently get their health information, and who they would trust to receive this type of information. More research in the area of northern health and risk communication is necessary in order to compare results to other regions across northern Canada and to determine best practices. In order to create more culturally significant and relevant contaminant health messages, researchers and government must invest time into determining ways that will be well received and heard by the communities they are working with and be adaptable based on the region, a community. For instance, in the Sahtú region, this could include using methods such as the local radio, friends and relatives, researchers or other health workers (nurses, etc.) as the most trusted sources to receive this type of information. Another consideration is assuring that these messages are understood when disseminated. In communities of the Sahtú, this means that providing information about contaminants must be translated in local languages or having translators to disseminate results of research projects. We can use these results as a baseline to compare with other health communication projects happening in northern Canada and other circumpolar Indigenous communities and regions. This thesis has provided further context in disseminating contaminant and health and risk communication messaging and suggestions to improve communication strategies.</abstract>
			<url hash="d17b5018">G18-3001</url>
			<doi>10012/14028</doi>
			<bibkey>Brandow-2018-Country</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Civil and Environmental Engineering, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2018</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Biogeochemical Signatures of the Great Lakes Watersheds</title>
			<author>
				<first>Qualbe Shadman</first>
				<last>Chowdhury</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Water quality in many regions of the Great Lakes Basin (GLB) has deteriorated due to numerous anthropogenic drivers, including increases in agricultural area, increased fertilizer use, intensive livestock production, and increases in human population densities. Excessive nutrient inputs from both point and non-point sources have accelerated eutrophication in inland watersheds and in receiving water bodies, and policy goals have recently been set to reduce phosphorus loading to Lake Erie by as much as 40%. Under such pressures, it is crucial to better our understanding of nutrient transport across the GLB and to identify key watershed drivers of both seasonal and annual nutrient loading from watersheds to the lakes. In this research study, I have utilized numerous metrics to characterize nutrient dynamics in Great Lakes Watersheds across a gradient of human impacts and have attempted to identify key controls on biogeochemical signatures.  As a part of this work, I paired water quality data from over 200 Great Lakes watersheds with land use and climate data to identify dominant controls on stream nutrient concentrations at the annual, seasonal, and event scales. At the annual scale, standardized regression analysis identified significant relationships between flow-weighted concentration (FWCs) and selected catchment characteristics. FWCs were found to be strongly linked to land-use variables such as combined agricultural and urban land, wetlands and tile drainage. Our quantification of these relationships was used to create spatial maps of annual nutrient concentrations and loads and to identify nutrient hotspots across the GLB. Specifically, high nutrient concentrations and export were observed in the Maumee and Sydenham River catchments, whereas lower concentrations and loads were found in Lake Superior catchments. At the seasonal scale, three primary seasonal nutrient regimes were identified: (1) ‘in-phase’ (positive correlation between monthly concentrations and discharge), (2) ‘out-of-phase’ (negative correlation), and (3) ‘stationary’ (no significant relationship). While in-phase seasonality was found to be the most common concentration regime for watersheds with higher levels of agricultural land use, nitrate seasonality in particular was found to be muted in watersheds with the highest agricultural land use, but to be more extreme in watersheds with less agriculture but higher amounts of forested area and higher wetland densities. Out-of-phase seasonality was found to be significantly associated with higher population densities and higher percent urban areas. At the event-scale, concentrations were found to be more variable with discharge for phosphorus than for nitrate. Additionally, Lake Erie showed significantly lower concentration variability in relation to discharge compared to all the other Lakes. As the Lake Erie basin also has higher agricultural land use than the other lakes, the more chemostatic concentration dynamics in these watersheds appears to be linked to agricultural nutrient use and suggests that agricultural nutrient legacies may be an important driver of current patterns in nutrient delivery to the lakes.</abstract>
			<url hash="4cac68a1">G18-4001</url>
			<doi>10012/13624</doi>
			<bibkey>Chowdhury-2018-Biogeochemical</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>