<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G19">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Civil and Environmental Engineering, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2019</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Application of a Hydrological Model for Predicting River Ice Breakup</title>
			<author>
				<first>Genevieve</first>
				<last>Brown</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>In cold regions, the breakup of river ice can be a significant event, resulting in flooding and damage to communities. Given the severity of such events, it is desirable to be able to predict the timing and severity of breakup. Limited progress has been made on forecasting breakup related flooding as no deterministic model of the breakup process and ice jam formation exist. Current tools for predicting breakup rely on developing a relationship between the previous winter conditions and the current spring conditions, with the understanding that a rapid or large runoff with a thick ice cover has the potential for a more severe breakup than if ice has had time to melt. These tools are largely empirical, statistical, or soft computing methods which rely on historical data sets of discrete observations to relate the complex relationship between climate and hydrology to breakup conditions and are limited by access to the extensive data required.  Within the current prediction methods, the application of hydrological models for forecasting breakup timing and severity is limited. Hydrological models can address some of the limitations of current tools, as they are able to simulate the complex relationships between climate and hydrology which has a strong influence on the breakup period. Additionally, hydrological models may be more practical in regions with limited data, as they can simulate variables of interest instead of relying on large historical data sets.  This thesis demonstrates how a hydrological model can be used to predict the timing and severity of breakup, through the coupling of a 1D river ice model with a hydrological model. Emphasis is placed on the development of the hydrological model to ensure that it provides realistic results throughout the basin.   The Liard basin, a large relatively data sparse river basin, in northern Canada is used as a case study. A thorough calibration strategy, based on an iterative, multi-objective approach is used in the development of the model. The final model exhibits strong performance in both calibration and validation throughout the basin. A simple 1D river ice model in MATLAB is coupled with the hydrological model.    The hydrological model can forecast the timing of breakup well based on the timing of the initial rise in the hydrograph. Breakup severity is predicted using a simple threshold model based on ice thickness, flow, and accumulated shortwave radiation. The prediction method was applied to an independent location as verification of the methodology with promising results.</abstract>
			<url hash="b02e4b36">G19-1001</url>
			<doi>10012/15285</doi>
			<bibkey>Brown-2019-Application</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Typologies of Nitrogen Surplus Across Continental US: Shifting Hotspots and Dominant Controls</title>
			<author>
				<first>Danyka Kimberly</first>
				<last>Byrnes</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Flows of reactive nitrogen (N) have significantly increased over the last century, corresponding to increases in the global population. The pressures on the N cycle include human waste, fossil fuel combustion as well as increasing food production (i.e., increasing fertilizer consumption, biological N fixation, and livestock manure production). The result is humans causing a 10-fold increase in the flow of reactive N globally. The influx of anthropogenic N into aquatic environments degrades water quality, alters fresh and saline ecosystem productivity, and poses an increasing threat to drinking water sources. In the U.S., decades of persistent hypoxic zones, created by elevated concentrations of nitrate from the landscape, have altered ecosystem trophic structure and productivity. Additionally, increasing N contamination of groundwater aquifers places over 20% of the U.S. population at increased risk of diseases and cancers.   Despite billions of dollars of investment in watershed conservation measures, we have not seen proportional improvements in water quality. It has been argued that delayed improvements in water quality can be attributed to legacy stores of N, which has accumulated in the landscape over many decades. There is considerable uncertainty associated with the fate of N in the landscape; however, studies quantified increasing stores of N in the subsurface, suggesting increasing stores of N in groundwater aquifers, in soil organic nitrogen pools, and the unsaturated zone. Nevertheless, the spatial distribution of legacy N across the conterminous U.S. is poorly quantified.   Here, we have synthesized population, agricultural, and atmospheric deposition data to develop a comprehensive, 88-year (1930 to 2017) dataset of county-scale N surplus trajectories for the U.S. N surplus, defined as the difference between N inputs and usable N outputs (crop harvest), provides insight into the trends and spatial distribution of excess N in the landscape and an upper bound on the magnitude of legacy N accumulation.   Our results show that the spatial pattern of N surplus has changed drastically over the 88-year study period. In the 1930s, the N inputs were more or less uniformly distributed across the U.S., resulting in a few hotspots of N surplus. The following decades had sharp increases in N surplus, driven by the exponential use of fertilizer and combustion of fossil fuels. Contemporary N surplus distribution resembles a mosaic of varying degrees of excess, concentrated in the heavily cultivated areas. To understand dominant modes of behavior, we used a machine learning algorithm to characterize N surplus trajectories as a function of both surplus magnitudes and the dominant N inputs. We find ten primary clusters, three in crop dominated landscapes, four in livestock dominated landscapes, two in urban dominated landscapes, and one in areas minimally impacted by humans. Using the typologies generated can facilitate nutrient management decisions. For example, watersheds containing urban clusters would benefit from wastewater treatment plant upgrades. In contrast, those dominated by livestock clusters would have more success in managing nutrients by implementing manure management programs.  The estimates of cumulative agricultural N surplus in the landscape highlights agronomic regions that are at risk of large stores of legacy N, possibly leading to groundwater and surface water contamination. In these agronomic regions, the average cumulative N surplus exceeds 1200 kg-N/ha by 2017. Despite having minimal agricultural activity in urban areas, urban fertilizer use has led to an average cumulative N surplus of over 900 kg-N/ha. While our estimates are an upper bound to legacy stores, significant uncertainty remains regarding the magnitude of the estimate of N accumulation. However, our results suggest that legacy N is at varying degrees, impacting most counties in the U.S.   The significant investment and corresponding lack of returns can lead to disillusionment in farmers, watershed managers, and the general public. Developing such N surplus typologies helps improve understanding of long-term N dynamics. Beyond refining the supporting science, appropriately communicating uncertainties and limitations of water quality improvements to the stakeholders, authorities, and policymakers are essential to continuing efforts to improve national water quality.</abstract>
			<url hash="29271a8c">G19-1002</url>
			<doi>10012/15336</doi>
			<bibkey>Byrnes-2019-Typologies</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="3">
			<title>The Urban Metabolism of the Greater Toronto Area: A Study of Nitrogen and Phosphorus Fluxes across the Urban, Suburban, and Rural Continuum</title>
			<author>
				<first>Melani-Ivy</first>
				<last>Samson</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>It has been predicted that approximately 65% of the developing world and 85% of the developed world will be living in cities by 2050. Toronto, the largest city in Canada and the fourth largest in North America, is expected to double in population in the next 50 years. Although such rapid urbanization can lead to enormous social, economic, and environmental change, little is understood about how population growth in Toronto and the “Golden Horseshoe” region around Lake Ontario will impact the ecological systems of Southern Ontario.  In our study, we are particularly interested in the ways in which increasing population densities in the Greater Toronto Area are impacting nutrient flows across Southern Ontario’s urban/rural continuum and how changing nutrient dynamics may lead to increasingly impaired water quality in Lake Ontario and beyond. In this work, we utilize a mass balance approach to quantify the flow of nutrients through urban, suburban, and agricultural areas of the Greater Toronto Area. A wide range of factors are considered, including human behaviour, domestic animals, stormwater management, and wastewater treatment processes. The present results suggest that any study of urban metabolism must take into account not only nutrient flows within urban boundaries, but must also identify externalities of urban development associated with a range of processes, from global trade to regional waste management.</abstract>
			<url hash="5e202a1a">G19-1003</url>
			<doi>10012/14658</doi>
			<bibkey>Samson-2019-The</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="4">
			<title>Recoupling the Livestock Nutrient Economy: A Path forward for Water Quality Improvement</title>
			<author>
				<first>Alexander</first>
				<last>Werenka</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Intensification of farming operations and increased nutrient application rates have led to higher crop yields and greater food security. At the same time, widespread use of commercial nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) fertilizers and large-scale livestock production have led to unintended environmental consequences, including eutrophication of both coastal and inland waters, threats to drinking water, and increased production of N2O, a potent greenhouse gas. In the past, crop and livestock production were typically more integrated, allowing most livestock to be fed by local crops, and most livestock manure to be applied directly to nearby cropland. Under current intensive agriculture practices, however, there is frequently a spatial decoupling of crops and livestock, leading to hot spots of manure production and a lack of opportunities for cost-efficient and environmentally sensitive disposal. In recent years, there has also been increased interest in the use of both farm and regional-scale bioreactors to convert excess manure to energy, thus exploiting a renewable energy source and increasing the potential to recycle animal waste.  In the present work, I develop a spatially distributed optimization approach to identify hotspots of manure production, and, using both economic and environmental criteria, evaluate the economic feasibility of (1) transporting manure for spreading on cropland to meet established nutrient requirements, and (2) constructing biogas reactors to process excess manure in areas where long-range transport is found to be infeasible. This work is focused on manure redistribution, and potential for biogas construction at the continental US scale. In order to identify the spatial disconnect between livestock and crop production, I developed a gridded data set where each cell was 6 km x 6 km and calculated the crop requirements and manure production in each cell. After finding the P requirements in each cell, I found that 530,000 tonnes of phosphorus in manure was located in areas where, if applied, it would be in excess of the local crop requirements.  I then examined the feasibility of transporting manure from excess locations (cells) to other locations to use as fertilizer by formulating an optimization problem to maximize the financial benefits of transporting the manure. Savings from transporting manure was calculated as the financial benefit from buying less mineral fertilizer minus the cost of transporting the manure. The solution to this optimization problem shows that transporting manure was able to reduce the excess phosphorus applied to fields by at least 88% with savings of up to $3 billion USD. Finally, I examined the costs and benefits of using the remaining excess manure (after transportation for fertilizer) as fuel to operate biogas plants. For this, I formulated an optimization model to site biogas plants across the continental US such that net profits from the biogas plants were maximized. Biogas net profits were defined as the money made from selling electricity minus the annualized costs for constructing and operating the biogas plants and transporting the manure to the biogas plants. The solution to this problem shows that constructing and operating 387 biogas plants yielded a net profit of $100 million USD and would utilize all of the manure remaining after transportation for fertilizer. This 100% utilization rate of excess manure would have great environmental benefits in terms of removing potential sources of non-point source pollution from farms that would otherwise be available to runoff into waterways.</abstract>
			<url hash="c044bfb9">G19-1004</url>
			<doi>https://dataverse.scholarsportal.info/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.5683/SP2/MFQP9L</doi>
			<bibkey>Werenka-2019-Recoupling</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth and Environmental Sciences, Doctoral Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2019</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Interactions of Phosphate and Silicate with Iron oxides in Freshwater Environments</title>
			<author>
				<first>Md Abdus</first>
				<last>Sabur</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Internal phosphorus loads, from bottom sediments to surface waters, are often comparable in magnitude to external phosphorus loads, particularly in water bodies with a history of high external phosphorus inputs from point and non-point sources. The benthic release of phosphorus can be influenced by several factors including pH, redox potential, temperature, microbial activity and the concentration of competitive anions at or near the sediment-water interface. Dissolved silicate occurs ubiquitously in natural waters and may act as a competitive ion to phosphate. Nonetheless, prior to the work in this thesis, the effect of silicate on internal phosphorus loading remained poorly understood. This thesis addresses several of the mechanisms through which silicate may influence the mobilization of aqueous phosphate from sediments in aquatic environments. The thesis starts with a thorough literature review of phosphorus biogeochemical cycling in relation to eutrophication, sediment-surface water interactions, mineralogy, competitive anions and microbial activity (Chapter 1). Next, adsorption/desorption of phosphate on/from goethite, a model ferric (hydr)oxide mineral, is investigated in the absence and presence of dissolved silicate. The influence of dissolved silicate on phosphate adsorption is evaluated through laboratory experiments and application of the CD-MUSIC model (Chapter 2). The results show that increasing concentrations of silicate decrease phosphate adsorption, leaving more phosphate in the aqueous phase. The competitive effect of dissolved silicate is more pronounced under alkaline conditions. Subsequently, phosphate desorption experiments were conducted under dynamic pH conditions in the presence and absence of silicate (Chapter 3). The experimental results show that the gradual transition from acidic to alkaline conditions induces the desorption of phosphate adsorbed to goethite under acidic conditions. The presence of silicate in the phosphate/goethite system does not affect phosphate desorption, because of the stronger surface complexation of phosphate to goethite. In addition to adsorption and desorption processes, the co-precipitation of phosphate with iron and the potential subsequent dissolution of these co-precipitates as a result of changing physico-chemical conditions may also control the mobility of phosphate in aquatic environments. The effects of dissolved silicate on the co-precipitation of phosphate with iron and the reactivity of the resulting solids are examined (Chapter 4). Ferric (co)-precipitates (i.e., Fe-P-Si) with variable Si:Fe ratios, were synthesized either via oxidation of Fe2+(aq) or by increasing the pH of Fe3+(aq) solution. The solids were characterized by a combination of chemical and spectroscopic techniques including attenuated total internal reflectance Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy (ATR-FTIR) and X-ray powder diffraction spectroscopy (XRD). Similar solid phase P:Fe ratios were found in co-precipitates formed from solutions with different dissolved silicate concentrations, regardless of the method of preparation. This suggests that the interactions between phosphate and iron during co-precipitation were not affected by dissolved silicate.  The ferric (co)-precipitates were subsequently reductively dissolved abiotically in buffered ascorbate-citrate solution to determine their reactivity under reducing conditions. The kinetic data show that the co-precipitates with higher Si:Fe ratios were more recalcitrant to dissolution. For co-precipitates synthesized via oxidation of Fe2+(aq), reductive dissolution experiments were also conducted in the presence of the facultative anaerobic iron reducing bacteria Shewanella putrefaciens. XRD analyses of the residual solids imply that solids with the higher Si:Fe ratios may be more resistant to microbially mediated reductive dissolution. The relative reactivities of the co-precipitates obtained by the two synthesis methods are also addressed in Chapter 4.  In Chapter 5, the effect of silicate on the mobility of phosphate in a natural sediment was evaluated via flow-through experiments. The results show that dissolved silicate enhances the mobility of phosphate at the sediment-water interface. Ferric (co)-precipitates were formed at the oxic surface of sediment columns via the oxidation of ferrous iron supplied with upflowing solutions containing variable silicate concentrations. The subsequent dissolution of these co-precipitates under imposed anoxic conditions at the sediment-water interface indicates that the co-precipitates formed at higher dissolved silicate concentrations were more reactive towards reductive dissolution. These results are therefore in apparent contradiction to those observed in Chapter 4. The ferric (co)-precipitates (i.e., Fe-P-Si) evaluated in Chapter 4 were prepared from solutions containing high concentrations of iron, phosphate and silicate, by imposing either rapid aeration or pH increase. These conditions were selected to maximize the yield from the syntheses. The synthesis methods in Chapter 4 are therefore most representative of aquatic environments where co-precipitation occurs rapidly (e.g., groundwater springs) and the concentrations of these dissolved constituents are fairly high. However, in many other aquatic environments, the diffusion-controlled release of Fe2+(aq) from the deeper sediments results in the gradual oxidation of Fe2+ at the sediment-water interface under oxic conditions. This process is typical in lake sediments with minimal advective exchange between surface water and groundwater. This gradual oxidation (at relatively low concentrations of Fe2+) results in the slow formation of ferric (co)-precipitates which may be dissimilar to those synthesized herein and discussed in Chapter 4. The ferric (co)-precipitates synthesized with the flow-through column system in Chapter 5 may be better analogues of slow forming co-precipitates in diffusion dominated or moderately advection influenced aquatic sediments than those synthesized in Chapter 4. 	Finally, to elucidate the likely importance of the various influences of dissolved silicate on phosphate mobility investigated in this thesis, concentrations of dissolved phosphate and silicate as well as pH data are extracted from the US National Water Information System (NWIS) network (data shown in Chapter 1 and Chapter 2). The NWIS data along with combined experimental and modeling results suggest that silicate-mediated phosphate mobilization is likely a commonly occurring process at the sediment-water interface of lakes and reservoirs. This thesis also demonstrates the multiple roles of silicate on the mobilization of phosphate in aquatic environments, and improves our fundamental knowledge of iron, phosphorus and silicon cycling in freshwater environments.</abstract>
			<url hash="a29be4d8">G19-2001</url>
			<doi>10012/14575</doi>
			<bibkey>Sabur-2019-Interactions</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth and Environmental Sciences, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2019</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Phosphorus Legacies and Water Quality Risks: A Vulnerability-Based Framework in Southern Ontario</title>
			<author>
				<first>Tamara</first>
				<last>Van Staden</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Excess phosphorus (P) loading increases the frequency of harmful algal blooms (HABs), posing severe threats to drinking water security and aquatic ecosystems. Efforts to reduce the inputs of P to Canadian agricultural soils started in the late 1970s-early 1980s, and were initially successful, but surface water P loading became persistent again in the 2000s. HABs were a problem in the southern Laurentian Great Lakes (LGL) before the initial nutrient mitigation efforts, and the re-emergence of HABs in Lake Erie in the 2000s was in part a result of legacy P that had accumulated in soils and groundwater in agricultural watersheds. Legacy P exists as a result of historical inputs of P, typically fertilizer used in excess of crop needs. Consequentially, even after reducing P inputs, legacy P continues to be exported from soils after several decades. In Chapter 2, a large-scale mass balance was conducted for the Ontario watersheds to locate and quantify agricultural and other anthropogenic P inputs from 1961 to 2016, utilizing existing datasets as well as historical reconstructions of P inputs to the landscape. This scale of P mass-balance has not been completed before in Ontario. The mass balance model was implemented into a Geographical Information System (GIS) platform to delineate potential areas with legacy P accumulation and depletion within the landscape. These maps identified areas with high P inputs and large potential stores of legacy P. Historically, southwestern Ontario has had the densest agriculture and populated areas in Ontario and has had high P inputs over time. County-scale trends such as shifts to intensive livestock or crop-based agriculture, or increasing urbanization were also identified. In Chapter 3, the fate and transport of P and the possible development of P legacies was explored in the context of risk. P export is influenced by environmental conditions in soil, as such, there is spatial variance in the likelihood that P will runoff or accumulate in soils. The environmental conditions may therefore be used to represent the vulnerability of the system and the risk to either lose or accumulate P. The cumulative agricultural P surplus map was used in conjunction with vulnerability maps to construct soil P risk maps. Different vulnerability models were explored, and ultimately soil erosion potential maps were used to identify vulnerable areas with a high risk of P losses to surface water and areas with a high risk of P accumulation in soil. It was determined that there was a higher risk of P accumulation in soil along the coast of Lake Erie, and it is possible that P legacies exist in these areas. The results inform nutrient management and abatement strategies and the adaptive implementation of conservation practices.</abstract>
			<url hash="1a2783bd">G19-3001</url>
			<doi>10012/15357</doi>
			<bibkey>Van Staden-2019-Phosphorus</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Examining Hydrogeological Processes in Freezing Soils using Remote Geophysical and Numerical Techniques</title>
			<author>
				<first>Brittney</first>
				<last>Glass</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The work presented in this thesis aimed to demonstrate the use of remote geophysical methods and numerical modelling to address questions related to hydrogeological processes in freezing soils. Two different study areas and research questions were investigated: In chapter 1, Landsat 4-5 TM and RapidEye-3 datasets were used to identify groundwater discharge zones in the Central Mackenzie Valley of the Northwest Territories. Given that this area is undergoing active shale oil exploration, identification of groundwater discharge zones is of great importance. Discharge zones represent groundwater-surface water interaction points that are potential pathways for contaminants associated with hydraulic fracturing to move. Following the works of Morse and Wolfe (2015), a series of image algorithms were applied to imagery for the entire Central Mackenzie Valley, and for the Bogg Creek Watershed (a sub watershed of the CMV) for selected years between 2004 and 2017. The algorithm series extracted ‘icings’ from the images. Icings (also called aufeis) are surface ice lenses where groundwater discharges in the winter months, then freezes. Icings were statistically examined for all of the selected years to determine whether a significant difference in their occurrence and size existed. It was concluded that there was a significant difference in the spatial distribution of icings from year to year, but that there were several places where icings were recurring. During a field visit in August of 2018, high resolution thermal imagery was captured for several of these locations and it was found that groundwater was also discharging in the summer. This provides strong evidence to suggest that the recurring icings represent springs from which groundwater discharges year-round. These springs represent ideal locations to monitor the quality of discharging groundwater following the establishment of fracking operations. Furthermore, identifying these monitoring points remotely is expected to have drastically reduced the field efforts that would have been required to find them in situ. This thesis demonstrates the value of remote geophysical methods for hydrogeological applications, particularly in areas that have limited accessibility.  The second component of this thesis establishes a conceptual model that describes the processes which influence winter subsurface pipe and water main breakage in Southern Ontario. Recent winters in this region have seen a dramatic increase in the number of pipe/main breaks that occur above the regional water table, but below the freezing front. Though subsurface pipe breakage is well-understood in saturated conditions or in the case when it is encompassed within the freezing zone, it is not well understood in the conditions of unsaturated soil which is not frozen, but contains a frozen zone above it. It is hypothesized that differential stress may be exerted on a pipe as soils of different frost heaving potential freeze and expand above the pipe. Once a certain overburden pressure is exceeded and upward frost heaving is no longer possible, it is expected that subsequent freezing will exert force onto the soil skeleton (and therefore pipe) below it. Two specific conceptual problems are developed in this work, and the processes which affect the distribution of stress in each case are described in detail. Then, a plan for the numerical implementation of each problem using the finite element model ABAQUS is given. Though the numerical models are not shown in this work, the conceptual models provide the framework which is necessary to implement a successful numerical model. The problem of pipe breakage in the unsaturated zone is complex and requires the coupling of equations which describe groundwater flow, stress-strain in a porous medium, and heat transport. Therefore, it was vital for an in-depth conceptual understanding of the problem to be established before introducing the numerical application.</abstract>
			<url hash="832ed207">G19-3002</url>
			<doi>10012/14466</doi>
			<bibkey>Glass-2019-Examining</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geography and Environmental Management, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2019</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Quantifying coniferous subalpine tree transpiration and source water under seasonal and hydrological stress in the Canadian Rocky Mountains, Kananaskis, Alberta</title>
			<author>
				<first>Lindsey</first>
				<last>Langs</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Fresh water supplies in mountainous regions are at risk as snow and ice stores continue to decline under rising global temperatures, earlier winter snowmelt and changing climate regimes. Alpine forests are of particular importance due to their hydrological connectivity within watersheds controlling groundwater base flow, influencing evapotranspiration (ET) and snow storage dynamics. A change in the water availability to subalpine vegetation via changes in winter snowpack accumulation and quantities or differing summer precipitation (P) regimes could have a drastic effect on the long-term health of these forests. This makes it imperative to understand and quantify their hydrological connectivity within these watersheds. Study sites located at Fortress Mountain in Kananaskis, Alberta are composed of co-occurring coniferous tree stands of Abies lasiocarpa and Picea engelmannii. Little is known about water use dynamics of these species at high elevations, specifically the quantity and timing of transpiration (T) in addition to the water sources most important for T during the entire length of the growing season. This study used a combination of hydrological and meteorological tools to address coniferous subalpine tree water use behaviours before, during and after the growing season (June-September). Methodologies focussed on determining seasonal T patterns using the non-invasive stem-heat balance method to determine sap flow and eddy covariance to capture stand ET. The source water of the studied trees was determined using δ18O and δ2H stable water isotopes and further partitioned using the MixSIAR Bayesian Mixing Model (BMM). Groundwater monitoring wells, soil tensiometers, P gauges, and meteorological stations were used to determine baseline environmental conditions. Stable water isotopes δ18O and δ2H were collected from all source waters (P, snow cover, soil water, groundwater) in addition to xylem water samples from the coniferous trees within the study area. Understanding tree response to P and drying events was the main objective addressed, yielding stark differences between the growing seasons of 2016 and 2017. Stand T was higher in 2017 (165 mm) than 2016 (118 mm) despite a much drier and warmer season (155 mm of rain in 2017 compared to 283 mm in 2016). A deeper, sustained snowpack in 2017 coupled with higher net radiation allowed for higher T rates. Paired with δ18O and δ2H stable isotope source partitioning, this study was able to identify soil water as the most important source to season-long tree productivity, with groundwater the most important for early growing season. Well-drained soils and shallow depth to bedrock inhibited groundwater access for the studied trees after the snowmelt period concluded. Thus soil moisture supplied a majority of water to the tree population during mid growing season, determined both hydrometrically and isotopically. Dry conditions in 2017 showed a clear trend between soil moisture levels and tree water use, with 2016 having almost double the soil moisture and tree productivity in the tail end of the growing season. By closely examining the patterns of subalpine tree water use, we can begin to clarify how these important ecosystems services will be impacted under a changing climate in addition to helping us better manage our forest and freshwater resources.</abstract>
			<url hash="87f0bb04">G19-4001</url>
			<doi>10012/14741</doi>
			<bibkey>Langs-2019-Quantifying</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Microclimatic Effects of Forest to Peatland Transitions Within the Boreal Plains</title>
			<author>
				<first>Adam</first>
				<last>Green</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Peatlands cover approximately 50% of the total landscape of the Western Boreal Forest, which includes the sub-humid Boreal Plains (BP) ecozone. The BP experiences persistent water deficit conditions, promoting anaerobic conditions, which has the potential to increase decomposition, transforming the peatlands from carbon sinks to carbon sources. With evapotranspiration (ET) being the dominant source of water loss in the BP, peatland persistence is hydrologically precarious, and as such, it is necessary to understand the dynamics and controls on ET within these systems. Due to the heterogeneity of the landscape, surrounding upland forests often shelter peatlands from wind. This results in spatially varying evaporative rates, which can influence surface moisture and vegetation regimes across a peatlands surface. High-resolution turbulent models allow for such flow scenarios to be resolved as they resolve flow in a 3D domain. Therefore, high-resolution turbulent models are essential in assessing the spatial variability of stresses placed on surface scalars such as ET, by displacement height transition.  This study uses a canopy resolving large-eddy simulation (RAFLES) to study the impact of displacement height transitions on surface-atmosphere exchanges of moisture within peatlands of the BP. The dimensions, vegetation structure and energy dynamics of the modeled peatlands were generated from observations of natural peatlands of the BP. Within the sheltered region leeward of a backward-facing step transition, the simulated peatlands experienced higher resistances to surface-atmosphere exchanges of moisture when compared to the reattachment and recovery regions. However, this trend was muted when the surface roughness of the peatland was increased as the roughness lowered the overall resistance of the surface. This study also found that the length of the peatland did not influence the flow reattachment dynamics within the peatland. However, it was observed that the peatlands with a narrow shape and a curved front-facing step geometry resulted in faster regional wind velocities. Understanding the turbulent dynamics within heterogeneous landscapes can help to control the rate and variability of surface to atmosphere exchanges of moisture within disrupted and reclaimed landscapes which can increase the predictability of moisture demands within future landscapes.</abstract>
			<url hash="1ef9eabe">G19-4002</url>
			<doi>10012/14605</doi>
			<bibkey>Green-2019-Microclimatic</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="3">
			<title>Deeper Burning Increases Available Phosphorus, Promotes Moss Growth, and Carbon Dioxide Uptake in a Fen Peatland One-Year Post-Wildfire in Fort McMurray, AB</title>
			<author>
				<first>Christine</first>
				<last>van Beest</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Carbon storage in northern peatlands is estimated to be ~795 Tg, equivalent to ~40% of atmospheric CO2.  Peatlands  are  dominant features of the Western Boreal Plains (WBP), which are experiencing a regime shift to a warmer and drier climate, as well as an increase in forest fire disturbance. Burning of the upper layers of rich organic matter peat releases enormous quantities of C to the atmosphere. The projected response of peatlands to forest fire is concerning, but widely understudied and could be of the utmost importance for the biogeochemical function and future net C balance of peatland. Impacts of climate change driven drying on peatland nutrient dynamics have been explored previously, however, the impacts of wildfire on nutrient dynamics have not been examined. This study assessed the impact of wildfire on N and P bioavailability and nutrient mineralization, plant nutrients balance, and the C and macronutrient stoichiometry and stock in a fen one-year post-wildfire by comparing a Burned and Unburned area. The results show that bioavailable P increased up to 200 times in surface water leachate, 125 times in groundwater and 5 times in peat. Surface ash leachate had increased concentrations in ammonium (NH4+) and nitrate (NO3-), and through groundwater mobility, the entire fen experienced increased bioavailable N. Mineralization of N and P were minimal at the Burned sites, relative to Unburned sites. Fire affected plant nutrient limitation patterns, switching from dominantly N-limited to NP co-limited in moss and P-limitation in vascular species. Burned site C stock (~14000 kg/ha) was higher relative to the Unburned site, which also increased CN and CP ratios. These findings suggest that long-term effects of elevated C, N, and P concentrations on plant productivity and decomposition must be re-evaluated for fire disturbance to understand the resiliency of peatland biogeochemistry post-wildfire.  Environmental controls, including hydrologic, biologic, and edaphic variables modified by the fire and their effect on CO2 fluxes have not been studied holistically. In this thesis, I studied a treed fen burned during the Horse River wildfire in Fort McMurray, AB, comparing CO2 fluxes between a Burned and Unburned area of the fen. We see that both gross ecosystem productivity (GEP) and total respiration (Rtot) were reduced in magnitude at the Burned sites in comparison to the Unburned site, with peak fluxes in the Unburned site occurring in late June, whereas the Burned site CO2 fluxes peaked later in the growing season. GEP and net ecosystem exchange (NEE) increased in carbon uptake in the Burned sites along a depth of burn (DOB) gradient, with the deepest burned areas having an increased potential to uptake more CO2 than the Unburned site. The data also showed that both bioavailable P and moss recolonization were highest in the deepest burned areas. Unburned environmental controls on CO2 fluxes were dominated by soil temperature, whereas the Burned sites CO2 fluxes were controlled by leaf area index. One-year post-wildfire, the deepest burned areas had between 5-200 times greater concentration of P than the Unburned site, the most moss recolonization, and the greatest CO2 uptake, showing that deeper burning could potentially increase the recovery trajectory and resiliency of northern peatlands after fire disturbance.</abstract>
			<url hash="69feda28">G19-4003</url>
			<doi>10012/14429</doi>
			<bibkey>van Beest-2019-Deeper</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="5">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Civil and Environmental Engineering, Doctoral Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2019</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Bedload sediment transport regimes of urban gravel-bed rivers under different management scenarios</title>
			<author>
				<first>Elli</first>
				<last>Papangelakis</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Watershed urbanization profoundly alters the hydrologic characteristics of urban rivers compared to their rural counterparts. This change in hydrologic conditions in combination with alterations to the sediment supply regime in urban watersheds leads to adjustments to channel form and the widespread degradation of urban rivers. Urban river management increasingly attempts to balance the societal needs of flood and erosion control, while simultaneously improving the ecological health or waterways. Two common types of river management include stormwater management (SWM), which focuses on the attenuation of urban floods, and in-stream restoration, which attempts to reconstruct stable and ecologically favourable channels. However, current urban river management designs lack consideration of the key process responsible for channel stability and habitat availability: bedload sediment transport. Two reasons for this shortcoming are the lack of bedload sediment data in urban watersheds and the consequent gap in understanding of the bedload transport dynamics of urban rivers. Consequently, the degradation of urban rivers persists. This project investigates bedload transport dynamics in urban rivers with different management scenarios to focus on four themes: (1) how urbanization affects bedload transport dynamics and its relationship to channel morphology, (2) how to best predict bedload transport dynamics in urban rivers, (3) how current urban river management strategies change the transport dynamics of rivers, and (4) how to improve bedload sediment monitoring technology. This project focuses on the grain-scale bedload transport dynamics of coarse material because it links to the morphodynamics and ecological processes of channels, it provides insights on the exact controls and spatial variability of bedload transport, and the responses to individual flood events can be directly measured. The overarching goal of this study is to contribute to improved urban river management strategies that focus on adaptive management and interdisciplinary approaches. Bedload sediment transport was monitored using RFID tracer stones in three streams with different hydrologic settings: rural, urban with no SWM, and urban with SWM. High-resolution water level data confirmed the hydrologic differences expected from the three watershed conditions, as well as channel enlargement characteristic of urban rivers. Results demonstrate that the morphologic differences between the study streams can be linked to changes in the grain-scale bedload transport dynamics of the streams. Bedload transport is accelerated in the urban stream due to an increase in the frequency of bedload mobilization, particularly of coarse sediment sizes. In contrast, SWM hasdecreased the bedload transport to an immobile and armoured state indicative of a competence-limit transport regime. Results are used to make recommendations for improved urban river management. Results from the bedload tracking were used to build predictive models of tracer displacements. A new variable that captures both the mobility and travel length of bed particles is introduced. Several flow metrics developed in the literature in rural and laboratory settings are calculated, and their ability to predict tracer displacements in the three streams is tested. Scaling tracer travel lengths by mean channel width collapses the data into a single, strong relationship with cumulative energy expenditure, providing a single model that can be used across systems with different watershed conditions. To assess the impact of an in-stream riffle-pool channel reconstruction on bedload sediment dynamics, bedload transport and morphologic change was monitored in adjacent unrestored and restored reaches of an urban channel. Results reveal that the restored reach is stable and self- maintaining, mirroring bedform maintenance processes in natural riffle-pool streams. However, the construction is more successful at slowing down the transport of coarse sediment more than fine sediment, leading to a coarse sediment discontinuity that may be contributing to accelerated channel adjustment beyond the limits of the constructed riffle-pool sequences. This project highlights the importance of considering the entire channel corridor when designing and monitoring restoration projects. A large limitation of bedload sediment tracking technology is the inability to determine the vertical position of tracers, which hinders the ability to study vertical mixing and translate tracer data into bedload transport rates. A new Radio Frequency Identification (RFID) bedload tracer stone is presented, along with results of laboratory performance tests. This new bedload tracer improves upon existing bedload sediment monitoring technology by providing the ability to measure the burial depth of tracers without disturbing the bed. An important contribution of this study is the extensive dataset of bedload transport collected in urban rivers. This study attempts to move away from descriptive differences in the characteristics of urban rivers compared to rural streams, and towards a process-level understanding of the anthropogenic effects on river systems. Grain-scale bedload transport theory, developed in rural and laboratory settings, is applied to urban settings to gain insights into the effects of urbanization and common river management strategies on the geomorphic processes of urban rivers. Recommendations for improved urban river management are developed from the results of this thesis.</abstract>
			<url hash="3f4cdc61">G19-5001</url>
			<doi>10012/15295</doi>
			<bibkey>Papangelakis-2019-Bedload</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="6">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>School of Public Health and Health Systems, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2019</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Mercury Exposure Analyses Amongst Dene and Métis Communities of the Northwest Territories</title>
			<author>
				<first>Leicester</first>
				<last>Fung</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Background: Fish is an important food source for many Indigenous communities within the Dehcho and Sahtú regions of Northwest Territories (NWT). However, environmental toxicants, such as mercury (Hg), can bioaccumulate and biomagnify to reach detectable levels in fish, particularly among predatory fish species. From a public health perspective, Hg exposure and biomonitoring assessments are invaluable assets that can highlight potential risk factors and evaluate risks associated with Hg toxicity. With the current body of knowledge, exposure assessment models conservatively account for Hg bioaccessibility in fish to be 100% because of the limited information available. Past literature have also noted statistical differences in Hg bioaccessibility with respect to food source as well as food preparation methods. As such, there is a need for more Hg biomonitoring and Hg bioaccessibility assessments to elucidate the relationships between dietary and demographic determinants with respect to Hg exposure. Objectives: Hg biomonitoring component. 1) To determine internal Hg exposure levels (blood and hair) from six Indigenous communities in the Dehcho and Sahtú regions of NWT. 2) To conduct t-test analysis for internal Hg exposure levels with respect to sex. 3) To construct simple linear regression models between internal Hg exposure levels with the following factors: i) age ii) non-piscivorous fish consumption iii) piscivorous fish consumption.   Hg bioaccessibility component. 1) To characterize Hg concentrations for uncooked and dried by smoking (dried/smoked) lake whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis). 2) To determine Hg bioaccessibility in uncooked and dried/smoked lake whitefish. 3) To conduct t-test analysis to determine Hg concentration and Hg bioaccesibility differences between uncooked and dried/smoked whitefish. Methods: Hg biomonitoring component. 150 Dene and Métis participants, between the ages of 6-79, were recruited from Deline, Fort Providence, Hay River Reserve, Kakisa, West Point First Nation and Jean Marie River of NWT. Blood and hair samples were collected for internal Hg exposure assessments. Participants were also asked to provide demographic information and complete a food frequency questionnaire (FFQ) for describing potential determinants of Hg exposure. T-test analysis and log-linear simple regression models were used to identify individual relationships.  Hg bioaccessibility component. Five whole lake whitefish (Coregonus clupeaformis) were used to investigate Hg bioaccessibility. Subsamples were subjected to two treatments: uncooked and dried/smoked. All dried/smoked and uncooked fish samples underwent a single phase (gastric only) IVBA model treatment. All Hg concentrations were expressed as wet weight and determined using an Ohio-Lumex portable mercury analyzer with pyrolyzer attachment. Results: Hg biomonitoring component. Hg levels in blood and hair were highly linearly-correlated with one another (r= 0.854, p&lt;0.05) and all of the participants had blood and hair Hg levels below 20μg/L and 6μg/g respectively. T-test analysis found no statistical differences (p&gt;0.05) when comparing blood Hg levels of male and female participants (2.711 ± 2.616 µg/L and 2.667 ± 4.079 µg/L respectively) Similarly, T- test analysis found no statistical differences (p&gt;0.05) when comparing hair Hg levels of male and female participants (0.868 ± 0.925 µg/L and 0.671 ± 0.866 µg/g respectively). According to the simple regression model’s findings, age was the only statistically significant factor and was positively associated with blood and hair Hg levels (B=0.020 and p&lt;0.01; B=0.011 and p&lt;0.01). Based on simple regression model’s findings, piscivorous fish consumption was not significantly associated with either Hg levels found within blood and hair (B= 0.068 and p&gt;0.05; B= 0.023 and p&gt;0.05). Similarly, non-piscivorous fish consumption does not appear to be significantly associated with blood and hair Hg levels (B= 0.022 and p&gt;0.05; B= 0.035 and p&gt;0.05) Hg bioaccessibility component. After culinary treatment, dried/smoked whitefish samples retained, on average, 46% of their original mass (i.e., due to moisture loss). As a result of moisture loss, the initial Hg concentration in dried/smoked whitefish samples (0.194 mg/kg) was significantly greater (p=0.002) relative to uncooked whitefish samples (0.080 mg/kg). When comparing Hg bioaccessibility, dried/smoked whitefish (53%) was statistically lower (p&lt; 0.001) compared to uncooked whitefish (102%). Despite the reduction in Hg bioaccessibility for dried/smoked whitefish, the bioaccessible Hg concentration in dried/smoked whitefish (0.101 mg/kg) was significantly greater (p&lt; 0.05) compared to uncooked whitefish samples (0.081 mg/kg). The loss of moisture mass and the increased density of Hg within dried/smoked whitefish samples were likely responsible for the increase in total and bioaccessibile mercury in dried/smoked whitefish. As such, dried/smoked whitefish samples had greater amounts of Hg digested and solubilized in aqueous solution. Conclusion: Both simple regression and static IVBA models’ findings have provided additional information for characterizing Hg exposure among participating communities in Northwest Territories.  Based on the study population’s demographic determinants and dietary patterns, age  is a key factor for understanding and predicting Hg exposure in the Northwest Territories. Bioaccessibility findings suggest source apportionment models that incorporate differences in Hg concentration between raw and smoked/dried fish may also need to account for the corresponding difference in bioaccessibility. For further generalizability of IVBA model’s findings, additional in vitro bioaccessibility studies using different fish species are needed. This research is important because it highlights dietary factors, such as cooking method, are potentially important to human exposure. Inclusion of such factors to source apportionment model may help further characterize the relationship between internal Hg exposure levels detected in biomarkers and the external exposure estimates.</abstract>
			<url hash="2df9738f">G19-6001</url>
			<doi>10012/14333</doi>
			<bibkey>Fung-2019-Mercury</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>