<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<collection id="G22">
	<volume id="1">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geography and Environmental Management, Doctoral Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Phosphorus Responses to Soil Moisture in Southern Ontario Agricultural Soil</title>
			<author>
				<first>Stephanie</first>
				<last>Higgins</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Agricultural landscapes are known to increase phosphorus (P) losses to waterways, contributing to the eutrophication of freshwater surface water bodies. In cold agricultural regions, the nongrowing season drives annual P transport and discharge. Previous research has focused on discharge from fields and watersheds to understand P dynamics in response to hydroclimatic events such as snowmelt and rain storms. Although P supply in soils has been considered a dominant mechanism driving P runoff, the dynamic nature of this supply on an annual basis in response to climate drivers is poorly understood. The goal of this thesis is to determine climatic (seasonal, moisture and temperature) controls on the supply of soluble P in agricultural soils. Two experiments were set up: one in a field setting and the other in a lab setting. The field study involved a snow-manipulation experiment in an agricultural field, in which soil P pools and net transformation rates were quantified under snow and limited-snow conditions. The lab experiment explored the impacts of frost severity, frost duration, frost cycle number and moisture addition on soil concentrations of water-extractable soluble reactive P (SRP), total dissolved P (TDP) and Olsen P, microbial biomass P, aggregate stability, and concentrations of SRP, TDP and TP (total phosphorus) in leachate draining from cores. In both studies, frost magnitude did not significantly impact soil P fractions or supply. Although soil water extractable P (WEP) was greater during the non-growing season than summer, this was not impacted by increased frost due to the removal of snow cover. The lab study also showed that frost magnitude did not impact P supply; however, both frost duration and moisture additions appeared to affect P supply. Water extractable P was positively related to moisture content in both experiments. An improved understanding of climate drivers on P cycling is needed in light of climate change. This thesis suggests that the supply of P may be impacted by a changing climate, but more due to moisture shifts rather than temperature.</abstract>
			<url hash="eb01a168">G22-1001</url>
			<doi>10012/18192</doi>
			<bibkey>Higgins-2022-Phosphorus</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Remote sensing of chlorophyll-a in small inland waters</title>
			<author>
				<first>Amir Masoud</first>
				<last>Chegoonian</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Small inland waters (SIWs) – waterbodies smaller than 100 km2 – are the predominant form of lakes globally, yet they are highly subject to water quality degradation, especially due to harmful algae blooms (HABs). Space-borne remote sensing has proven its capability to detect and map HABs in coastal waters as well as large waterbodies mostly through estimating chlorophyll-a (Chla). However, remote retrieval of near-surface Chla concentration in SIWs is challenging due to adjacency effects in remotely sensed signals and substantial in situ optical interferences of various water constituents. Although various algorithms have been developed or adapted to estimate Chla from moderate-resolution terrestrial missions (~ 10 – 60 m), there remains a need for robust algorithms to retrieve Chla in SIWs. Here, we introduce and evaluate new approaches to retrieve Chla in small lakes in a large lake catchment using Sentinel-2 and Landsat-8 imagery. In situ Chla data used in this study originate from various sources with contrasting measurement methods, ranging from field fluorometry to high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC). Our analysis revealed that in vivo Chla measurements are not consistent with in vitro measurements, especially in high Chla amounts, and should be calibrated before being fed into retrieval models. Calibrated models based on phycocyanin (PC) fluorescence and environmental factors, such as turbidity, significantly decreased Chla retrieval error and increased the range of reconstructed Chla values. The proposed calibration models were then employed to build a consistent dataset of in situ Chla for Buffalo Pound Lake (BPL) – 30 km length and 1 km width – in the Qu’Appelle River drainage basin, Saskatchewan, Canada. Using this dataset for training and test, support vector regression (SVR) models were developed and reliably retrieved Chla in BPL. SVR models outperformed well-known commonly used retrieval models, namely ocean color (OC3), 2band, 3band, normalized difference chlorophyll index (NDCI), and mixture density networks (MDN) when applied on ~200 matchups extracted from atmospherically-corrected Sentinel-2 data. SVR models also performed well when applied to Landsat-8 data and data processed through various atmospheric correction (AC) processors. The proposed models also suggested good transferability over two optical water types (OWTs) found in BPL. Based on prior evaluations of the models’ transferability over OWTs in BPL, locally trained machine-learning (ML) models were extrapolated for regional retrieval of Chla in the Qu’Appelle River drainage basin. The regional approach was trained on in situ Chla data from BPL and retrieved Chla in other six lakes in the drainage basin. The proposed regional approach outperformed a recently developed global approach (MDN) in terms of accuracy, and showed more applicability than local models given the scarcity of in situ data in most lakes. In addition, ML models, e.g., SVR, performed consistently better than other models when employed in the regional approach.  A rare phenomenon of marked blue discoloration of ice and water in winter 2021 in Pasqua Lake, a small lake in Qu’Appelle Watershed, provided an opportunity to assess the regional approaches in estimating chlorophyll-a for waterbodies where enough training data is not available. Therefore, using a developed model based on data from BPL, we produced Chla maps and could successfully relate the discoloration event to a late fall bloom in Pasqua Lake. We included the details of that study in Appendix A. Altogether, the models and approaches introduced in this thesis can serve as first steps toward developing a remote-sensing-based early warning system for monitoring HABs in small inland waters. Results showed that the development of an early warning system for SIWs based on Chla monitoring is currently possible, thanks to advancements in medium-resolution satellite sensors, in situ data collection methods, and machine learning algorithms. However, further steps need to be taken to improve the accuracy and reliability of systems: (a) in situ data need to be consistent for being fed into remote sensing models, (b) retrieval models and AC processors should be improved to provide better estimations of Chla, and (c) regional approaches might be developed as alternatives for local and global approaches in the absence of accurate AC processors and scarcity of in situ Chla data.</abstract>
			<url hash="7208f0d2">G22-1002</url>
			<doi>10012/17981</doi>
			<bibkey>Chegoonian-2022-Remote</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="2">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Biology, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Assessment of remote Patagonian riverine fish using environmental DNA</title>
			<author>
				<first>Erika Alexandra</first>
				<last>Burton</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Freshwater systems and fish communities face many anthropogenic threats such as climate change, pollution, and invasive species, causing a rapid loss of biodiversity. To protect freshwater fish basic knowledge of their numbers, distribution, and habitat is required, but can be difficult to obtain. Remote freshwater systems can experience human impacts but are even less understood due to lack of access and potential hazards. Patagonia (the southern tip of South America) is sparsely populated but contains many freshwater systems that can be indirectly impacted by human activities. The introduction and subsequent naturalization of several invasive salmonid species in rivers and lakes. Despite the potential for adverse effects on these ecosystems, they are generally under researched and uncharacterized. One such freshwater environment is the rivers draining from the stratovolcano Melimoyu in northern Chilean Patagonia, where limited access, high flows and considerable river debris makes traditional sampling from boats or wading impractical or dangerous. New biomonitoring techniques such as environmental DNA (eDNA) detection can be used to sensitively and non-invasively obtain data of species presence or even community structure through analysis of water samples and may provide an avenue for obtaining data about freshwater communities in remote systems such as Melimoyu. Applying eDNA barcoding or metabarcoding techniques in remote systems may allow researchers to gain knowledge about the biota in these environments where traditional sampling may be limited or impossible. Environmental DNA barcoding was used for the detection of three different fish species: invasive brown trout (Salmo trutta) and Atlantic salmon (Salmo salar), and native puye (Galaxias maculatus) in the rivers draining Volcán Melimoyu. Brown trout eDNA was detected at seven sites across four rivers, Atlantic salmon eDNA was not detected at any sample sites, and puye eDNA was detected in one river with high certainty. At several sites eDNA detection techniques were accompanied by backpack electrofishing. The detection of brown trout eDNA was potentially influenced by differing environmental conditions (e.g., flow) between sampling events. Puye was not always detected by eDNA despite being collected during electrofishing. eDNA can be a powerful biomonitoring tool for detection of fish in remote systems, especially if applied with consideration of controls for contamination, transport, and storage of samples. Samples for eDNA barcoding can be collected under less-than-ideal conditions, and with an appropriate sampling regime, applied to remote systems to obtain valuable data on distributions of individual fish species. However, in future studies eDNA metabarcoding (i.e., simultaneous detection of all fish eDNA present using universal primers) may be a more powerful tool for use in remote freshwater environments to gain an understanding of entire communities. Collections of supplementary data could be used to inform occupancy models for a better understanding of the eDNA and presence of fish in these freshwater systems. This study demonstrates the potential application of eDNA for informing resource managers about fisheries resources, even in areas where traditional fisheries techniques are difficult or impractical to complete.</abstract>
			<url hash="f9b40e86">G22-2001</url>
			<doi>10012/18176</doi>
			<bibkey>Burton-2022-Assessment</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="3">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>School of Public Health and Health Systems, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Supporting Inuvialuit Food Sovereignty: Characterizing Culture-Centered Dietary Messages for Healthy, Safe and Culturally Appropriate Diets in the Inuvialuit Settlement Region, Northwest Territories</title>
			<author>
				<first>Julia</first>
				<last>Gyapay</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Contemporary Inuit diets are comprised of both country and store-bought foods, which each confer benefits and risks to Inuit physical, mental, cultural, spiritual and socio-economic health. Inuit residing in Inuit Nunangat (the Canadian traditional homelands of the Inuit) disproportionately experience food insecurity and impacts of climate change, threatening the quality and safety of foods consumed. Elevated concentrations of certain environmental contaminants in Inuit Nunangat represent a concerning source of Inuit dietary exposure to contaminants through country food consumption. Further, Inuit are experiencing disconcertingly high rates of chronic diseases, are consuming less nutritious and culturally significant country foods, and are consuming more unhealthy, non-nutrient dense store-bought foods. It is therefore imperative that Inuit communities have access to evidence-informed and culturally relevant information promoting healthy and safe diets to support their nutritional and cultural well-being. Dietary messages addressing the health risks and benefits of country and store-bought food choices and activities in the Inuvialuit Settlement Region (ISR) of the Northwest Territories (NWT) aim to reduce harm and improve health among Inuvialuit (Inuit from the Western Arctic). However, an understanding of how dietary messages are developed and disseminated in the ISR remains unknown and best practices for collaborative approaches to nutrition communication grounded in Inuvialuit culture and knowledge is understudied. This project aims to fill these gaps in knowledge, extending our understanding of dietary message communication strategies in Inuit communities. The purpose of this thesis is to (1) Characterize current public health dietary messages in the ISR (Study 1); (2) Identify how territorial, regional and local dietary message disseminators, local country food knowledge holders, and the public in Tuktoyaktuk can co-develop culture-centered dietary messages to more effectively promote healthy, safe and culturally appropriate diets in the community (Study 2); and (3) Provide recommendations to territorial, regional and local dietary message stakeholders to further improve dietary messaging in the ISR and NWT (Studies 1 and 2). This study utilized an Indigenous research paradigm and community-based participatory and decolonizing research approaches. An in-person interview (n=1) (February 2020) and telephone interviews (n=13) (May-June 2020) were conducted with key informants (health professionals, government employees and community nutrition program coordinators) in Inuvik, Tuktoyaktuk, Paulatuk and Yellowknife (Study 1). An Inuvialuk community researcher conducted storytelling interviews with country food knowledge holders (n=7) and community members (n=3), and a talking circle with local public health dietary message disseminators (n=2) between June-July 2021 in Tuktoyaktuk (Study 2). Follow-up key informant telephone and videoconference interviews with territorial and regional dietary message disseminators (n=5) were completed in June 2021 (Study 2). Interviews were analyzed using thematic analysis. The findings indicated that dietary messages disseminated to the public in the ISR are developed at all scales and communicated by territorial and regional (allied) health professionals, territorial and regional health department representatives, regional and local food program coordinators, academic researchers, country food knowledge holders and local leadership through a variety of in- person, written, audio and online methods. Country food knowledge holders communicate their own messaging through the sharing of Inuvialuit knowledge while harvesting and preparing country food in their communities. Public health dietary messages focus predominantly on a) healthy store-bought food choices, b) nutritional advice about store-bought and country foods and c) safety risks of consuming country foods. Federal and territorial messaging is seldom tailored to the ISR, lacking representation of the Inuvialuit food system and consideration of local food realities. Key barriers to regionally tailored, culture-centered dietary message development and dissemination in the ISR included a lack of collaboration between stakeholders involved in communications and limited resources required to develop trusting, respectful and collaborative relationships between dietary message stakeholders. Participants at all levels support increased inclusion of cultural and community perspectives about food to develop regionally and locally tailored dietary messaging, especially about country food harvesting and preparation knowledge and skills. Although most dietary message stakeholders wish to be involved in co- development processes, some country food knowledge holders desire leading traditional communications about country foods in Tuktoyaktuk. This project has made an important contribution to the literature on health and risk communication about country and store-bought foods in northern Indigenous communities by characterizing dietary messages disseminated in, for and within the ISR, examining residents’ awareness of messages, and identifying best practices for co-developing regionally and locally-tailored, culture- centered dietary messages in the ISR. Findings from this project have informed the creation of the Inuvialuit Food Messages Survey to evaluate the effectiveness of dietary messages as part of the ongoing Country Foods for Good Health project. Findings have also informed recommendations to NWT and ISR dietary message stakeholders to more effectively promote healthy, safe and culturally appropriate diets in Tuktoyaktuk and the ISR through the (co-) development and dissemination of culture-centered dietary messaging that supports Inuvialuit food sovereignty. Additionally, the process of conducting this thesis during the COVID-19 pandemic has led to methodological innovations for working remotely with community researchers and is able to provide key recommendations for researchers that can be used post- pandemic. These findings and recommendations have practical applications for other Inuit Nunangat regions and Canadian northern Indigenous communities interested in understanding and improving dietary messaging communication strategies.</abstract>
			<url hash="410869e3">G22-3001</url>
			<doi>10012/18061</doi>
			<bibkey>Gyapay-2022-Supporting</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="4">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Biology, Doctoral Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Use of water isotope tracers to elucidate hydrological conditions of lakes in the Peace-Athabasca Delta over space and time: A foundation for lake ecosystem monitoring</title>
			<author>
				<first>Casey</first>
				<last>Remmer</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Hydrological monitoring in complex, dynamic northern floodplain landscapes is challenging but increasingly important as these ecosystems come under threat from multiple stressors, including climate-driven decline in freshwater supplied by rivers draining the hydrographic apex of western North America. Sustainable approaches capable of tracking status, trends and drivers of lake water balances in complex, remote landscapes are needed to inform ecosystem stewardship and water-security actions. The Peace‐Athabasca Delta (PAD) in northern Alberta, Canada, is a Ramsar Wetland of International Importance reliant on episodic river ice‐jam flood events to recharge abundant perched lakes and wetlands. However, the frequency of these floods has been in decline for decades over much of its area.  Compounding concerns about water-level drawdown have prompted the need to improve knowledge of lake water balances and establish a lake monitoring program. Yet, the delta’s remoteness and dynamic nature present challenges to these goals. In this thesis, I address hydrological knowledge gaps essential to understanding spatial and temporal patterns of hydrological processes and their influence on lakes in the PAD. First, we assess the legacy influence of a large-scale ice-jam flood in 2014 on hydrological and limnological status of lakes in the PAD by integrating spatial and temporal data. Analysis of water isotope compositions and water chemistry measured at numerous lakes across the delta shows that hydro-limnological effects of the flood event of 2014 failed to persist beyond the early ice-free season of 2015. Isotope-inferred paleohydrological records from five hydrologically representative lakes in the PAD indicate that periodic desiccation during the Little Ice Age occurred at the most elevated basin in response to locally arid climatic conditions and reduced flood frequency, yet other lower elevation sites were influenced by high water level on Lake Athabasca owing to increased snowmelt- and glacier-derived river discharge. In contrast, water isotope data during the past 15 years at all five lakes consistently document the strong role of evaporation, a trend which began in the early to mid-20th century according to sediment records and is indicative of widespread aridity unprecedented during the past 400 yr. We suggest that integration of hydrological and limnological approaches over space and time is needed to inform assessment of contemporary lake conditions in large, complex floodplain landscapes.  Next, we use water isotope compositions, supplemented by measurements of specific conductivity and field observations, from 68 lakes and 9 river sites in May 2018 to delineate the extent and magnitude of spring ice‐jam induced flooding along the Peace and Athabasca rivers. Lake‐specific estimates of input water isotope composition (δI) using a coupled-isotope tracer approach were modelled after accounting for the influence of evaporative isotopic enrichment. Then, using the distinct isotopic signature of input water sources, we develop a set of binary mixing models and estimate the proportion of input to flooded lakes attributable to river floodwater and precipitation (snow or rain). This approach allowed identification of areas and magnitude of flooding that were not captured by other methods, including direct observations from flyovers, and to demarcate flow pathways in the delta. We demonstrate water isotope tracers as an efficient and effective monitoring tool for delineating spatial extent and magnitude of an important hydrological process and elucidating connectivity in the PAD, an approach that can be readily adopted at other floodplain landscapes. Finally, we use over 1000 measurements of water isotope composition at ∼60 lakes and 9 river sites during the spring, summer and fall of five consecutive years (2015–2019) to identify patterns in lake water balance over time and space, the influential roles of evaporation and river floodwaters, and relations with meteorological conditions and river water levels. Calculation of evaporation-to-inflow ratios using a coupled-isotope tracer approach, displayed via generalized additive models and geospatial ‘isoscapes’, reveal strongly varying lake water balances. Results identify distinct areas vulnerable to lake-level drawdown, given the likelihood of continued decline in ice-jam flood frequency, longer ice-free season duration and reduced snowmelt runoff. Results also demarcate areas of the delta where lakes are more resilient to factors that cause drawdown. The former defines the Peace sector, which is influenced by floodwaters from the Peace River during episodic ice-jam flood events, whereas the latter describes portions of the active floodplain environment of the Athabasca sector which receives more frequent contributions of Athabasca River floodwaters during both spring ice-jam and open-water seasons. Efficiency of water isotope tracers to capture the marked temporal and spatial heterogeneity in lake water balances during this 5-year time span, and their diagnostic responses to key hydrological processes, serves as a foundation for ongoing lake monitoring, an approach readily transferable to other remote and dynamic lake-rich landscapes.</abstract>
			<url hash="dcdf515a">G22-4001</url>
			<doi>10012/17890</doi>
			<bibkey>Remmer-2022-Use</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Development and application of paleolimnological analyses to disentangle the roles of natural processes and anthropogenic activities on contaminant deposition and hydrological conditions across a northern delta</title>
			<author>
				<first>Mitchell</first>
				<last>Kay</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Freshwater ecosystems across northern Canada provide important habitat for wildlife and have long supported the traditional lifestyles of Indigenous communities. Multiple potential stressors threaten the security of water supply to northern landscapes, which fosters need for information spanning broad spatial and temporal scales to inform adaptive and mitigative strategies. At the Peace-Athabasca Delta (PAD; northern Alberta), the world's largest boreal freshwater delta, existing data records have been too short and too sparse to resolve many concerns over the roles of major energy projects (hydroelectric regulation of river flow, oil sands development) and climate change on decline of flood frequency and magnitude and drawdown of shallow aquatic basins, and on supply of substances of concern. Intensive paleolimnological research during the past two decades at the PAD has evaluated past changes in contaminant deposition and hydroecological conditions to discern effects attributable to oil sands development along the Lower Athabasca River and to regulation of Peace River flow by the W.A.C. Bennett Dam. This thesis builds substantially on these previous studies to address knowledge gaps by applying conventional paleolimnological methods at new locations to improve understanding of temporal changes in contaminant deposition and hydrological change and developing an innovative paleolimnological approach for discerning variation in sediment sources over space and time to lakes within the PAD. 	Concerns of pollution in the PAD stem from potential for dispersal of contaminants released by bitumen mining and processing activities within the Alberta Oil Sands Region (AOSR), which straddle the Lower Athabasca River. Unfortunately, systematic monitoring began thirty years after onset of oil sands development and sampling locations have changed over time, which has hampered the ability to accurately track temporal trends or attribute sources of pollution at the AOSR and downstream locations. Previous paleolimnological studies in the PAD have provided critically missing baseline information by employing lake sediment deposited before oil sands development to evaluate lake or river-bottom sediment deposited after oil sands development for evidence of pollution. Results show no enrichment via fluvial or atmospheric pathways, however, analyses to date were limited to a sediment core from one upland lake and samples of river-bottom sediment collected from a few sites within the Lower Athabasca River and its distributaries within the PAD. In Chapters 2 and 3, contiguous measurements of trace elements (beryllium, chromium, lead, mercury, nickel, vanadium, and zinc) in lake sediment from floodplain and upland lakes were employed to develop knowledge of pre-disturbance concentrations, and to quantify the extent of enrichment in lakes at the PAD since onset of oil sands mining and processing activities via fluvial and atmospheric pathways, respectively. Results demonstrate no enrichment since onset of oil sands development via fluvial pathways. Also, no enrichment via atmospheric pathways was detected for vanadium, nickel and total mercury (THg) at upland lakes coincident with the onset of oil sands activities. Total mercury enrichment was detected at the start of the 20th century in sediment cores from two upland lakes, which is congruent with stratigraphic patterns observed in many other lake sediment records in response to long-range anthropogenic emissions across the northern hemisphere.  	Site-specific paleolimnological studies from four regions spanning large-scale bitumen mining on the Lower Athabasca River to gold mining in central Northwest Territories (including AOSR, PAD, Slave River Delta (SRD), Yellowknife region of central NWT) have provided a wealth of information about temporal patterns of deposition of substances of concern. Differences in laboratory methods and data analysis, however, have challenged ability to compare and contrast site-specific studies among regions. Opportunity to coalesce the current state of knowledge was capitalized on in Chapter 4 via systematic re-analysis of concentrations of key pollution-indicator trace elements in sediment cores from 51 lakes spanning the four key regions. Lake sediment records from lakes within the mining regions (AOSR and central Northwest Territories) illustrate enrichment of pollution-indicators since onset of mining and processing activities via atmospheric pathways, while no enrichment was detected at the PAD or SRD via fluvial pathways since onset of mining activities. The knowledge generated from Chapters 2-4 can be employed by multiple stakeholder groups to assess risks associated with contaminant dispersal across a vast region of northwestern Canada.  	Long-term perspectives provided by paleohydrological studies at the PAD have demonstrated that decline of flood frequency and magnitude and lake-level drawdown began decades before onset of Peace River flow regulation by the W.A.C. Bennett Dam. Many of these studies have been concentrated in the northern Peace Delta but concerns also exist about declines in river discharge, flood frequency and lake levels in the southern Athabasca Delta. Chapter 5 tests the hypothesis that the Embarras Breakthrough, a natural geomorphic change in distributary flow of the Athabasca River, is the main driver of recent hydrological change in the Athabasca Delta. Stratigraphic variations in the mineral matter content of sediment cores from nine floodplain lakes, including at sites within the Athabasca River terminus region, demonstrate that flood influence increased after 1982 at lakes along a distributary to the north of the Embarras Breakthrough and declined at lakes east of the Embarras Breakthrough. The timing of this bi-directional change confirms that the Embarras Breakthrough has caused the largest shift in hydrological conditions within the Athabasca Delta during the past ~120 years.  	 Paleohydrological reconstructions employing conventional analyses have provided valuable insight into the hydrological evolution of the PAD but integration of the results across sites has remained a challenge due to marked differences in sediment composition across the spectrum of hydrological processes influencing lake water balances. At flood-prone lakes, physical methods (e.g., grain size, magnetic susceptibility) provide high information content, whereas biological or bio-geochemical methods (e.g., diatoms, plant macrofossils, cellulose oxygen isotope composition) provide high information content at perched basins. Elemental concentrations, however, can be determined accurately along the full gradient of mineral-rich to organic-rich sediment of flood-prone and perched basins, respectively, and can be used to delineate the three major sources of sediment supplied to lakes (Athabasca River, Peace River, and local catchment), which is a key advancement over previous paleolimnological studies. In Chapter 6, a mixing model framework was developed and evaluated via application to sediment cores from two adjacent lakes in the Athabasca Delta. Output from the mixing model aligns remarkably well with conventional loss-on-ignition analysis and paleohydrological interpretations from the same two lakes, which further illustrate the profound effect of the 1982 Embarras Breakthrough on hydrological conditions of lakes in Athabasca Delta. Interestingly, model results indicated that ~60% of the sediment originated from the Peace River during the largest ice-jam flood event in the hydrometric record (1974). Due to the success of this model, opportunity exists to apply the model to a network of lakes in the PAD, where elemental concentrations have been analyzed, to reconstruct spatial and temporal variation of pathways of sediment sources and infer changes in hydrological processes. The methods developed and applied in this thesis are anticipated to be broadly applicable to other freshwater landscapes where monitoring records remain too short and too sparse to discern effects of multiple stressors.</abstract>
			<url hash="45d600e0">G22-4002</url>
			<doi>10012/18663</doi>
			<bibkey>Kay-2022-Development</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="5">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Geography and Environmental Management, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Snow Depth Retrieval from Wide Band Radar in Trail Valley Creek</title>
			<author>
				<first>Wei</first>
				<last>Wang</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Snow is an essential component in hydrology systems, and more speci cally, monitoring variations in snow cover can provide valuable information about water supply, wildlife habitats, and climate changes. In recent years, the potential of wide band snow radar (e.g. 2-8 GHz) has been discovered with a series of campaigns in Operation IceBrdige (OIB). Due to data from OIB mainly focusing on sea ice, most of the algorithms were also developed for snow on sea ice. As a result, this thesis aimed to test the applicability of the interface-based pulse peakiness snow depth retrieval method to snow on land. In addition, due to the common usage of radar altimeter in sea ice classi cation, this thesis also explored the possibility of adapting some of the ideas in sea ice classi cation to develop another retrieval method. Both approaches were tested on the 6 major vegetation types (tree, tall shrub, riparian shrub, dwarf shrub, tussock, and lichen) in the study area. Snow depth derived from Airborne Laser Scanner (ALS) point clouds was used as the reference for snow depth retrieval. Running the recalibrated pulse peakiness algorithm yielded a Mean Absolute Error (MAE) of 12 cm, 27 cm, 29 cm, 13 cm, 9 cm, and 10 cm for tree, tall shrub, riparian shrub, dwarf shrub, tussock and lichen respectively. It was concluded that the principles behind the pulse peakiness approach is valid for snow on land. The presence of surface vegetation and the hummocky terrain of the study area did present some considerable challenges. In comparison, the classi cation approach using K-means while produced some accurate results under speci c situations, was not as robust as the existing pulse peakiness approach. Although, it was argued that the classi cation approach was in early stages and there were some potential for better results.</abstract>
			<url hash="6463363f">G22-5001</url>
			<doi>10012/17915</doi>
			<bibkey>Wang-2022-Snow</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="6">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>Earth and Environmental Sciences, Master Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Quantifying the role of reservoirs in altering phosphorus dynamics using a combination of data analysis and process modeling</title>
			<author>
				<first>Tori</first>
				<last>Grootjen</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Excess phosphorus (P) from agricultural watersheds promotes eutrophication in downstream aquatic systems. Reservoirs retain P generated from farm fields and protect downstream waters. Reservoirs also act as hotspots for P transformation, as anoxic conditions can facilitate the release of stored P from the lake sediments. The role of inland reservoirs in P speciation at the watershed scale is relatively unexplored. This problem is growing in importance as approximately half of the global river volume is at least moderately impacted by damming, and is projected to reach 93% with all the planned or proposed dams (Grill et al. 2015). Here we use a decade of soluble reactive P (SRP) and total P (TP) concentration data at the inlet and outlet of two reservoirs, Belwood Reservoir and Conestogo Reservoir, in the Grand River Watershed, Canada. The annual SRP and TP percent retention varied at both reservoirs, showing that the reservoirs acted as a sink in some years and as a source in other years. The percent TP retention in Belwood Reservoir varies from -40% to 32%, while percent TP retention in Conestogo Reservoir is generally lower, between -72% to 25%. The SRP retention in Belwood Reservoir varied between -68% and 43%, while SRP retention in Conestogo Reservoir varied between -71% and 28%. Interestingly, the source-sink behaviour is visible for both SRP and TP and they are similar between years. That is, in years that Belwood Reservoir acts as a source of TP, the reservoir often acts as a source of SRP too. At the seasonal scale, we found that both reservoirs increase the proportion of bioavailable P (SRP:TP ratio) from inlet to outlet between April and October. We then built a process-based model to examine the P cycling and sediment-water interactions controlling this speciation of P in the Belwood Reservoir. The model was able to capture downstream SRP export with NSESRP = 0.57-0.86 and TP export with NSETP = 0.60-0.91. The model had difficulty capturing the SRP:TP magnification from inlet to outlet and sediment P accumulation, especially for the first few years of model simulation (2007 - 2012). Model results highlight the role of internal loading during the summer months. As dam construction is on the rise globally, it is critical to understand the impact of reservoirs on the relative reactivity of P in order to mitigate nuisance and potentially harmful algal blooms.</abstract>
			<url hash="76d699d1">G22-6001</url>
			<doi>10012/18207</doi>
			<bibkey>Grootjen-2022-Quantifying</bibkey>
		</paper>
		<paper id="2">
			<title>Evaluation of baseflow estimation methods with real and synthetic streamflow data from a watershed</title>
			<author>
				<first>Siyu</first>
				<last>Cheng</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>Baseflow with origins from groundwater is a critical component of streamflow sustaining it throughout the year especially during dry periods. To better understand the role of baseflow in streamflow, accurate estimates are needed. This study calculates baseflow through existing graphical and digital filter methods, using actual streamflow data from a gauging station at the Alder Creek Watershed (ACW) and synthetic streamflow data at ten study points within the same watershed simulated with HydroGeoSphere (HGS) (Aquanty Inc., 2018). There are four widely used graphical (Sloto and Crouse, 1996; Aksoy et al., 2008) and six digital filter (Lyne and Hollick, 1979; Chapman and Maxwell, 1996; Furey and Gupta, 2001; Eckhardt, 2005; Tularam and Ilahee, 2008; Aksoy et al., 2009) approaches for baseflow estimation being used and compared. To determine the most optimal estimation approach, baseflow estimates from real data are assessed based on the concept of hydrologic plausibility (Nathan and McMahon, 1990), while baseflow estimates obtained from the HGS streamflow record with graphical and digital filter methods are compared to those computed directly by HGS. Overall, results from this study indicate that baseflow hydrographs reveal a seasonal pattern. During wintertime, streamflow is composed almost entirely of baseflow, whereas during summertime, baseflow only consists approximately 20% to 60% of streamflow. After comparing the baseflow estimates with those computed by HGS, the most optimal approaches at ten points are assessed. Results show that the best approach for six points is the FUKIH (Aksoy et al., 2009) approach; for three points is the Chapman and Maxwell (1996) approach; and for one point is the Eckhardt (2005) approach. In conclusion, it is inferred that the most optimal approach within the ACW varies spatially.</abstract>
			<url hash="efdfc86b">G22-6002</url>
			<doi>10012/17977</doi>
			<bibkey>Cheng-2022-Evaluation</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
	<volume id="7">
		<meta>
			<booktitle>School of Environment, Resources and Sustainability, Doctoral Thesis</booktitle>
			<publisher>University of Waterloo</publisher>
			<address />
			<year>2022</year>
		</meta>
		<paper id="1">
			<title>Drivers and Implications for Water Governance: A case study of the western Lake Erie basin</title>
			<author>
				<first>Erin</first>
				<last>Mills</last>
			</author>
			<abstract>The purpose of this study was to better understand drivers of water problems and their implications for water governance scholarship and practice. Drivers here are identified as social and environmental forces affecting a system, such as a Great Lakes basin. Eutrophication in the western Lake Erie basin provides the empirical setting to achieve the study purpose, using the following objectives: (i) identify drivers of eutrophication in the western Lake Erie basin, (ii) determine whether these drivers are taken into account in nutrient management efforts, and (iii) assess the relationships among drivers and water governance. Two parallel cases of nutrient management, in the Canadian and United States’ (US) portions of the western basin, are explored using policy Delphi surveys with practitioners and researchers, and content analysis of formal nutrient management documents such as strategies and agreements. Findings from the research revealed that nutrient management efforts are identifying many of the same drivers (e.g., agricultural operations) that emerged from the data. Overlaps between the US and Canadian case studies indicate a shared understanding of the causes of eutrophication in the western Lake Erie basin. Areas of overlap between the policy Delphi surveys and document analyses within each of the case studies indicate shared perspectives from experts and formal nutrient management documents. These overlaps were expected, since Lake Erie is a transboundary body of water shared between Canada and the US, and the two countries have worked together for over a century to address water quality and quantity concerns through binational agreements and agencies. However, there were also differences in the sets of identified drivers of eutrophication that raised questions about the strength of shared understandings both within and between the US and Canadian case studies. For example, some drivers identified in the Canadian policy Delphi were not identified in the Canadian document analysis or in the US case study. These gaps indicate areas where nutrient management in the western Lake Erie basin could be improved through coordinated efforts to develop shared problem framings of eutrophication. The study findings empirically demonstrate the importance of identifying drivers when addressing water problems as well as the challenges that can occur when problem framings are mismatched within and across jurisdictions. When determining whether these drivers of eutrophication are taken into account by nutrient management efforts in the western Lake Erie basin, a similar pattern emerged. There was agreement among both the US and Canadian policy Delphi surveys and document analyses that several major drivers of eutrophication are taken into account in nutrient management efforts by multiple mechanisms ranging from research to regulation, including efforts involving agricultural operations. However, gaps were identified both within and between the US and Canadian case studies on whether some drivers of eutrophication are taken into account by nutrient management efforts. The concept of sufficiency emerged from Canadian and US policy Delphi participants. In this way, a driver may be taken into account to some extent, but these efforts were identified as insufficient to mitigate the driver as a cause of eutrophication. Together, these findings raise questions about the effectiveness of nutrient management efforts in the western Lake Erie basin. Specifically, the results suggest that the persistence of eutrophication may be due at least in part to a failure to take drivers into account. From the policy Delphi survey and document analysis data, evidence also emerged regarding the relationships between drivers and water governance. Existing framings of eutrophication do not explicitly identify water governance as a driver of eutrophication. The results demonstrated that water governance could be a driver of eutrophication, for example by shaping nutrient management actions. The results also showed that there are dynamic relationships among drivers of eutrophication and the water governance system, with influences moving bidirectionally across levels and scales. This empirical demonstration contributes to the currently understudied subject of driver directionality in the social-ecological systems and water governance literatures. This research makes several contributions to the water governance and SES literatures. The dissertation contributes to emerging discussions in the water governance literature on the importance of identifying and accounting for drivers, including their relationships with water governance, when addressing water problems. There are currently knowledge gaps on characterizing drivers within specific contexts and understanding the relationships between driver perception and management. I address these gaps by identifying the drivers of eutrophication in the western Lake Erie basin and determining whether those drivers are taken into account by nutrient management efforts. The use of the document analyses in combination with the policy Delphi surveys was a methodological approach that has not been widely used. In this research, the two methods provided nuanced and novel perspectives on drivers of eutrophication. In the eutrophication literature broadly, and in discussions of Lake Erie specifically, drivers of eutrophication are often framed as biophysical or socioeconomic factors. The identification of the water governance system and nutrient management efforts, including actors, policies, and program effectiveness, as drivers of eutrophication in the western Lake Erie basin is a contribution to the eutrophication literature that is unique to this research. This identification and characterization of water governance systems as a driver also adds value to other explorations of water problems and their associated water governance systems. Overall, the research contributes to understandings in the water governance literature on the relationships that exist between water governance and drivers by demonstrating that these relationships are bidirectional and exist across scales. The empirical findings of the research demonstrate the utility of regional case studies for filling identified knowledge gaps in the SES literature on understanding how drivers interact, how governance affects solutions to water problems, and how these relationships have influence across scales, as well as demonstrating the need for additional research.  The findings of this research also have implications for the empirical practice of water governance in the western Lake Erie basin. By identifying gaps in identifying drivers and accounting for drivers through nutrient management efforts, the research identifies opportunities to improve nutrient management efforts and water quality outcomes in the western Lake Erie basin. Specifically, there are differences in how drivers of eutrophication are understood and taken into account by nutrient management efforts. These differences indicate that work is necessary both within the Canadian and US jurisdictions as well as binationally to deepen the shared understanding of eutrophication and how its causes are perceived. To improve water quality in the western Lake Erie basin, it is necessary to critically examine nutrient management effectiveness and incorporate the novel drivers of eutrophication identified by the research into framings of eutrophication as well as nutrient management solutions.</abstract>
			<url hash="ce6afeb4">G22-7001</url>
			<doi>10012/18475</doi>
			<bibkey>Mills-2022-Drivers</bibkey>
		</paper>
	</volume>
</collection>